
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Categories on nkvl</title>
   <link>https://nkvl.xyz/categories/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Categories on nkvl</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2022 - Nikola Vlahovic</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://nkvl.xyz/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Blogging should be simple</title>
       <link>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/blogging-should-be-simple/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/blogging-should-be-simple/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;While designing this blog I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented
with fonts from Google Fonts, which is a service
providing a trove of wonderful typefaces. Eventually, I found
something fitting and added them to my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, I got rid of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The names are still there, so if you happen to have them
on your device, the site will look how I originally envisioned.
I&amp;rsquo;m considering removing even those.
The experience is now mainly designed for the humble and widely distributed
&amp;ldquo;Liberation&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Arial&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Times New Roman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these fonts are provided for you when accessing the website.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t happen to have any of them - I hope you&amp;rsquo;ll enjoy
whatever fallback your environment is equipped with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time and bandwidth dedicated to fonts reduced by a 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the investors are convinced, here are the real reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve read there are some issues&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
with the Google Fonts privacy policy and GDPR.
Apparently some efforts were made to alleviate them,
though I don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s become of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be bothered to look for alternative providers or
explore the precise details for distribution licensing of the specific fonts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to facilitate the collection of your personal
data. I care about my privacy, and I wish to extend that care
to the wonderful people visiting my little e-garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maybe-you-dont-need-fancy-fonts&#34;&gt;Maybe you don&amp;rsquo;t need fancy fonts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My design goals could be summarized as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintainability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, when it came to me in a dream that I should
make a blog, it turned out some dude already booked the domain I wanted.
It was past me.
He thought this operation would not need any docs,
while I wished he prepared for the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, not much to learn, and nothing broke.
This could&amp;rsquo;ve been a different story if there were more moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lets say I know all my libraries, build tools etc. and somehow they remained
stable for 2 years. Everything is properly documented.
The following is a non-exhaustive list of what else could change:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The dependencies could vanish from the CDNs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CDNs could vanish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your hosting provider could vanish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The privacy policies of the above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Licenses for the libraries and fonts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local laws.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What &amp;ldquo;local&amp;rdquo; is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep it simple, if you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rewis.io/s/u/zH2/&#34;&gt;GDPR ruling for serving a website with fonts from Google Fonts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Blog Update #1</title>
       <link>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/blog-update-1/</link>
       <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/blog-update-1/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;This website has been inactive for quite a while now.
&amp;ldquo;This is about to change!&amp;quot;, said the heart.
But you and I know better than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rhythm of posts will continue to be sporadic.
New articles will show up every other now-and-then,
and most probably not on a Monday.
I&amp;rsquo;ll negotiate with heart on the precise
details and inform you in due time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of, the blog was due some minor maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;minor-maintenance&#34;&gt;Minor Maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;https-only&#34;&gt;HTTPS only&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve enabled &lt;code&gt;Enforce HTTPS only&lt;/code&gt; on Github Pages.
That was so easy, I don&amp;rsquo;t know why I haven&amp;rsquo;t done this before.
It&amp;rsquo;s literally a checkbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;privacy-policy&#34;&gt;Privacy Policy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the updated privacy policy. I don&amp;rsquo;t
collect your data, but my hosting provider does.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>On Idempotent HTTP Requests</title>
       <link>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/idempotent-http-requests-intro/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 15:32:00 +0200</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/idempotent-http-requests-intro/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Idempotence is a common property among
web service resources. Many times it&amp;rsquo;s a given, but sometimes
you need to explicitly facilitate it yourself due to specific business and
reliability requirements. This post aims to clarify what is idempotence and
how the property provides certain safety guarantees which help us develop
more reliable and predictable web services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A request is idempotent if the intended effect of multiple identical
requests is the same as the effect of one such request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the previous definition, read-only
requests are clearly idempotent. Additionally, &lt;code&gt;DELETE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;PUT&lt;/code&gt; requests
should be implemented as such according to RFC7231. Lets break it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;idempotent-requests&#34;&gt;Idempotent requests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A read-only request like &lt;code&gt;HEAD&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;OPTIONS&lt;/code&gt; does not - in general - modify
the applications state. They might produce some side-effects like
writing access logs, but all in all they&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;intended&lt;/em&gt; for transfering, not changing, state.
No effect is the same effect, so they are idempotent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PUT&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;DELETE&lt;/code&gt; on the other hand, are intended for state modification. Intuitively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PUT&lt;/code&gt; should upsert a completely defined object. Calling PUT on the same resource with the same payload
several times should result in just one object with the given data existing. The first PUT creating
the object and the following ones updating it - but given that the payload is the same, the state
effectively remains the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calling &lt;code&gt;DELETE&lt;/code&gt; on a uniquely identifiable object results in the deletion of &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; that object. While
sending a &lt;code&gt;DELETE&lt;/code&gt; request on an endpoint several times might end up with a different response - the state
remains the same. You can&amp;rsquo;t really delete the same object twice.
Bulk delete semantics sometimes break this rule depending on the implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-non-idempotent-requests&#34;&gt;What are non-idempotent requests?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A request which increments a counter. Every subsequent call will increment the number, resulting in a different state each time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A request which exclusively adds to a collection. E.g. adding a comment to a BBS or adding a post to Facebook. POSTing a comment twice
results in duplicate comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generalizing - a non-idempotent request, when performed multiple times
with the same payload, results in multiple application state modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-idempotence-matters&#34;&gt;Why idempotence matters?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idempotence gives the client the ability to repeat a request without fear of causing trouble. This
creates a more predictable, smoother and user friendly experience by reducing the problems
user or network errors might introduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets examine a few scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;adding-a-post-to-a-website&#34;&gt;Adding a post to a website&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user is attempting to write a post to their website via a CMS. The admin
panel does so by sending a &lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; request to a specific resource on the server. The
&lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt; semantics are idempotent - specifically, the app sends the
title of the post, a description, the post itself, and a unique slug.
The slug uniquely identifies the post on the website.
An impatient user clicks the post button again, which sends another request to the server - this request is rejected
because a post with this slug already exists.
After a while, just one post appears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the service didn&amp;rsquo;t provide an idempotent resource for this action, this would
result in two posts being added to the website, with the user being forced to fix the problem
manually themselves. E.g. if instead of having an explicit, user set identifier - the slug - the
server itself generated a slug or other unique ID for the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sending-a-money-transfer-request-to-a-payment-api&#34;&gt;Sending a money transfer request to a payment API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets say your server is the back-end of a shopping website. You
manage user accounts, listings and shopping carts. Without idempotent
semantics, a user can order the same stuff multiple times by accident. Or even worse
your service might end up double or triple billing the same order, if not written very carefully to
mitigate any networking issues in communication to the third party service. Retrying requests to
the payment processor becomes non-trivial, prone to error and provider specific.
On the other hand, with idempotent
semantics you can rest assured the payment is guaranteed to occur only once with
many requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the previous example, double billing or double ordering is a far more significant
problem - in a lot of cases it&amp;rsquo;s very undesirable, needs a lot of steps to mitigate, and
depending on the transaction, can be very damaging to the reputation of a company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrap-up&#34;&gt;Wrap-up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idempotence can prevent user errors and mitigate networking issues by ensuring that
a given action results in the same state, no matter how many times we retry it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some errors can be costlier that others, with the benefits of idempotence easily outweighing
the costs of implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With that in mind, when choosing third-party providers, it may be wise to consider idempotence -
especially with payment APIs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors-note&#34;&gt;Authors Note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On 2022-11-27, the title was changed from &amp;ldquo;Retrying after the inevitable failure: Idempotent HTTP Requests&amp;rdquo;
to &amp;ldquo;On Idempotent HTTP Requests&amp;rdquo;. Along some other minor editorial changes,
I&amp;rsquo;ve also removed the announcements for another post demoing an implementation
since I&amp;rsquo;m focusing on other things right now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>The Compounding of Habits</title>
       <link>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/habits-you-are-what-you-do/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 23:33:13 +0200</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://nkvl.xyz/posts/habits-you-are-what-you-do/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;At some point in our lives, we are forced to face one simple truth - the time
we have on this earth is valuable and finite. Not a single
person so far was documented to live forever - the best offer I&amp;rsquo;ve seen only applies
&lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; we die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a realization we come to terms with many times as we age. Every moment begins to
count. We understand it becomes necessary to use our time wisely and deliberately
if we wish to better ourselves. Be healthier. Go out. Consume less and create more.
Floss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But decisions are &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Sticking to decisions is harder. Some goals are impossible to reach
fast and easy, by just making one decision. They demand &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; making the right decision.
That&amp;rsquo;s where habits come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;habits-stack-up&#34;&gt;Habits Stack Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drink 2 to 4 coffees a day, and I have been doing so for a couple of years.
Nothing unusual - one or two shots each morning and one in the afternoon after lunch.
Napkin math says I&amp;rsquo;ve guzzled down somewhere between 700 and 1200 coffees in the past year.
That&amp;rsquo;s starting to sound impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shot of espresso contains
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.caffeineinformer.com/caffeine-content/espresso&#34;&gt;anywhere between 25mg to 214mg of caffeine&lt;/a&gt;.
For the sake of simplicity, let&amp;rsquo;s say it contains 100mg. Drinking a 1000 espressos contains
a 100g of caffeine. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK532910/&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s about 10 lethal doses&lt;/a&gt;.
Over the time of one year I&amp;rsquo;ve consumed
enough coffee to kill two to three nuclear families. &lt;strong&gt;Doing something small every day
can have big results over a long period of time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five hundred push-ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A hundred books read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A thousand hours of piano practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things that sound daunting, yet achievable - a rep, page, or espresso at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;habits-short-circuit-decisions&#34;&gt;Habits Short-circuit Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing anything out of the ordinary requires effort.
I want to be healthier - that&amp;rsquo;s a decision. I&amp;rsquo;ll eat salad for lunch two times a week, a
nice small start - another one. On Tuesdays and Saturdays you will make
the hardest decisions yet - will I order a salad, or a pizza?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, habits are just things you do without giving them much thought.
You have dinner and watch TV. You brush your teeth before bedtime. You walk your dog,
go for a jog, make coffee and have breakfast in the same order most mornings.
You&amp;rsquo;re used to it. That&amp;rsquo;s just how you roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to make a &lt;em&gt;decision&lt;/em&gt; to drink coffee this morning.
The whole 7 minutes it took you from bed to coffee the conscious part
of you was doing other stuff. It&amp;rsquo;s easy and it feels good. The thing is - you &lt;em&gt;didn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; make
that decision right now. You were there for the ride.
There aren&amp;rsquo;t many occasions a person just sits down and takes a few minutes to weigh
the pros and cons of making a coffee. You&amp;rsquo;ve chosen what to do a long time ago, the moment
you&amp;rsquo;ve acquired the habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrap-up&#34;&gt;Wrap-up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often we find ourselves in need of bettering our lives. To do so requires
achieving goals by taking &lt;em&gt;decisive&lt;/em&gt; action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of these goals - like eating healthier, quitting coffee or
getting good at the piano - aren&amp;rsquo;t driven by one big decision, but rather
by consistently committing to lot of small ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your past self takes part in making certain decisions for the current you through your habits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeating a habit is easier than acting against it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;authors-note&#34;&gt;Authors Note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was edited on 2022-11-27, cleaning up some sentences
and changing the title from the pretentious and nonsensical &amp;ldquo;Habits: You are what you do&amp;rdquo;
to &amp;ldquo;The Compounding of Habits&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
